<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="docbook-xsl/xhtml/docbook.xsl"?> 

<article version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Generatrivia : board games generator</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Sebastián</firstname><surname>Gurin</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>softpoint</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>06-17-2010</pubdate>
  </info>
  
  <abstract><para>Generatrivia : board games generator javascript framework for easily define, publish and play, board games like chess, trivias, ludo on he web. </para></abstract>
   
  <revhistory>  
    <revision>
      <revnumber>0.01</revnumber>
      <date>20 July 2010</date>
      <authorinitials>sgurin</authorinitials>
      <revremark>Initial revision and release with only some sections</revremark>
    </revision>
  
  </revhistory>
  
   <section>
    <title>About this document</title>
  	<para>This document is available in the following formats:</para>  
  	<orderedlist>    
	  <listitem><formalpara><title>pdf</title><para>
	  <ulink url="../generatrivia.pdf">Generatrivia : board games generator for the web</ulink></para></formalpara></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><formalpara><title>html fragmented</title><para>
	  <ulink url="../generatrivia-htmls">Generatrivia : board games generator for the web</ulink></para></formalpara></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><formalpara><title>docbook (sources) </title><para>
	  <ulink url="../generatrivia.xml">Generatrivia : board games generator for the web</ulink></para></formalpara></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><formalpara><title>download htmls</title><para>
	  <ulink url="../generatrivia-htmls.tgz">Generatrivia : board games generator for the web</ulink></para></formalpara></listitem>
  
  	</orderedlist>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

	<para>Generatrivia: define, publish and play your board games in the web.</para>
	
	<para>Generatrivia is a html and javascript based application to define and generate boards games like chess, trivia, ludo, and games like that. 
	It supports tools that game definitions can use, like dices, question and answers, pieces definition and initial positioning, etc.
	The users who uses generatrivia for defining a game, must define the game in a text file (javascript - json format), indicating the game board image, 
	defining pieces (image, shape, size, color, name). If the game requires dices, the "dices tool" should be enabled. 
	If the game require questions and answers like in a trivia, questions answers, categories should have to be defined in that file as well. </para>
	
	<para>Once this game definition file is ready, the generatrivia javascript framework can be used for executing the game in a web page easily. </para>
	
	<para>In generatrivia generated games, the computer do not control any game logic. The players are responsible moving their pieces and in some 
	games perhaps creating the pieces too. Also players are responsible	of controlling that others do not cheat while moving them!! 
	This design has two main advantages:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>the games are defined by board image and rules outside computing. This gives a lot of flexibility for game definition.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>the computer ony replaces paper and dices, so the game experience is almost like the same as a paper made board.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para>Also, the framework contain a lot of known board game definitions, 
	like trivias, different kind of chess, checkers, ludo, etc. </para>
	
	<para>About the history of the project. The initial idea was to provide teachers with an easy mean of defining trivia games of school subject 
	so students can play agains each other in a single computer in the classroom. I realice that no game logic programming is required for this, since
	students are able of counting points and moving their game pieces by theirself. Then I realice that several board games (the ones that do not require cards), 
	can be sistematically defined for human players only.</para>
	
    
  </section>
  
  
  
  <section>
  <title>Getting starting</title>
  
  <para>No experience with programming languages is required for building your board games using generatrivia. 
  The user should know show to work with files, directories and editing text files. </para>
  
  <para>In this section, we will learn how to generate some simple game boards like ludo, trivia and chess.  
  step by step. </para>
  
  
  
  	<section><title>Making the ludo game</title>
  	
  	<para>in this section we will define our first game, the ludo game. Rules of the game can be fount at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludo_(board_game). 
  	The ludo game consist on the following elements: </para>
  	
  	 <itemizedlist>
	
	<listitem><para>A board</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>4 colored circular pieces of colors red, blue, yellow and green</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>A dice</para></listitem>
	
	<para>So we will define each of these things using generatrivia:</para>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  
	<listitem><formalpara><title>Prepare files</title>
	<para>First of all you have to download and decompress generatrivia somewhere. 
	Your game will be use some of these files.</para>
	
	<para>Second, we will prepare your game's directory and files. For this, simply copy generatrivia's src 
	directory to somewhere. Rename with your game's name, in this case "ludo".  This directory
	will be where your trivia game will be stored. All following steps will be working in this dir.</para>
	</formalpara></listitem>
	
	<listitem><formalpara><title>The board image</title>
	<para>Create or copy your game board's 'image from internet. Put in on your game's directory and call it ludoboard1.png. </para>
	
	<para>For our ludo we will use the following image:</para>
	
	<informalfigure>
	    <mediaobject>        
	      <imageobject>
	        <imagedata fileref="../examples/ludo/ludoboard1.png" format="png"/>
	      </imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>Our ludo game's board image</phrase>
	      </textobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	</informalfigure>
  
  
	</formalpara></listitem>
	
	<listitem><formalpara><title>Define the game in a text file</title>
	<para>The last and more important step is 
	to define all of our game's elements in a the game definition text file. For this, first create a file called data.js and open 
	it with your favourite plain text editor	
	<footnote><para>In windows, you must use a plain text editor like notepad, and not ms word. Also, in be sure the file 
	is called data.js and not something like data.js.txt</para></footnote>.
	</para>
	<para>For our first version of the ludo game, this will be the file contents:</para>
	
	<programlisting>
triviadata={
    gameName: "the Ludo game",
	
	boardImage: "ludoboard1.png",
	boardSize: "640,640",
	
	pieces: [
         {name: "red piece", code: "circle(10, 10, 10, 10)", 
        	 size: "20,20", color: "#ff0000"},
        	 
         {name: "blue piece", code: "circle(10, 10, 10, 10)", 
        	 size: "50,20", color: "#0000ff"},
        	 
         {name: "green piece", code: "circle(10, 20, 10, 10)", 
        	 size: "20,20", color: "#00ff00"},
        	 
         {name: "green piece", code: "circle(10, 20, 10, 10)", 
        	 size: "20,20", color: "#00ff00"}  
    ]
}
	</programlisting>  
	<para>The file contents must be a valid javascript - json object string. </para>
	
	<para>Let's introduce the data.js file and explain what 's inside briefly.</para>
	
	<para>First of all the game definition file is defined using the programming language json. 
	It is recommended but not mandatory that the user is familiarized with it: http://json.org/</para>
	
	<para>As you can see, there are some properties defined as gameName, boardImage, 
	boardSize and pieces. boardGame indicates what this game is called ("ludo"), and boardImage indicated the image file that will be used
	as game's board ("ludoboard1.png"). </para>
	
	<para>The more complex one is pieces. Remember we said the game ludo
	 consist in 4 pieces of color red, green, blue and yellow. So the "pieces" property is telling just that. The following 
	 code defines a single game piece (circular piece of size 20 x 20 pixel and color red-#ff0000): </para>
	 
	 <programlisting>
	 {name: "red piece", code: "circle(10, 10, 10, 10)", 
	  	 size: "20,20", color: "#ff0000"},
	 </programlisting>
	
	</formalpara></listitem>
	
	
	<listitem><formalpara><title>Ludo is ready</title>
	<para>If there are no errors in the data.js file we are ready. Simply open the file index.html with 
	your web browser and the game will start. and show something like this: </para>
	
	<informalfigure>
	    <mediaobject>        
	      <imageobject>
	        <imagedata fileref="imgs/ludogame1.png" format="png"/>
	      </imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>Our ludo game first screen</phrase>
	      </textobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	</informalfigure>
	
	</formalpara></listitem>
	
	
	<listitem><formalpara><title>Now create the pieces and play</title>	
	
	<para>In our ludo game, before playing the players must create the necesary pieces. Asuming 
	will be 4 players, we create 4 pieces of each colors red, blue, green and yellow and move them in the board
	to their initial positions. For moving the pieces, just add them and then drag them with the mouse to desired board position. 
	We perform this using the "Add Piece" tool at the left top corner: </para>
	
	<informalfigure>
	    <mediaobject>        
	      <imageobject>
	        <imagedata fileref="imgs/ludogame2.png" format="png"/>
	      </imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>Our ludo screen after we added four pieces of each color</phrase>
	      </textobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	</informalfigure>
	
	</formalpara>
	</listitem>
	
	<para>After all pieces are added to the board, the four players are ready to start playing. Roll the dices with 
	the button "Roll dices". </para>
	
	</itemizedlist>
	
	
  	
  	</section>
	
step 3) If the data is valid, your trivia is ready!! Simply open generatrivia.html in your browser for start playing.
  </section>
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <section>
  <title>Built in game tools</title>
  <para>The game is structered in the board, the pieces, and tools. Tools can be of several types: </para>
  
  	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>a game related activity tool like the dices tool, or the question and answer tool. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>a game developemnt heloper tool, like the piece position tool</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>any user defined tool...</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para>This section will teach you 1) give detailed information about using each built-in tool and 
	2) teach you how to program your own tools using the javascript framework's api. </para>
  
  
  
  
  <section><title>Pieces tool</title>
  <para></para>
  </section>
  
  
  
  <section><title>Dices tool</title>
  <para></para>
  </section>
  
  
  
  <section><title>Questions and answers tool</title>
  <para></para>
  </section>
  
  
  
   <section><title>Pieces position tool</title>
   
  <para>This tool is usefull when defining games that consists in several pieces with defined positions in the board, 
  like chess and checkers. With this tool, you can add all the games pieces manually using the pieces tool, each piece 
  with the correct size, color and position, and then clicking the button. When you are ready, press the tool's button 
  "get pieces porcentual info", and it will return all the "addPieces" code for data.js, so you only have to copy and 
  paste it, for your game to show the initial pieces in the board.</para>
  
  </section>
  
  </section>
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <section><title>Building custum tools</title>
  <para>In this section we will show you how to build your own custom tools with an example. It is required to know the 
  basis of javascript and html languages. </para>
  
  <para>A tool consists on the following elements: 1) some user interface like input widgets like buttons, text entries, etc. 
  that the player uses for controlling the tool. 2) some logic that do something related to the game. 3) some configuration in 
  data.js for the specific tool</para>
  
  <para>For example, the dices tool, consists on a button and text entry to 
  controlling the tool (roll dices button and a text for showing the dice result). It has no logic related to the game. 
  It can be configured using the "dices" property in data.js</para>
  
  <para>We will define an abstract tool</para>
  
  <programlisting>

/* a cutom tool (plugin) example : mouseCoords */
gt.tools.mouseCoords = {
                        
name: "mouseCoords",

description: "a tool that shows absolute and percentual position "+
	"of a point in the board on mouse click",

/**this method will be called by the frameowork for loading the tool, 
 * In this method the tools should create the markup in the
 * parent, register event listeners, etc. 
 * the tool shoud *append* a new element to the parrent.
 *  	
 * @param parentEl - is a dom object or an id or jquery selector for this 
 * tool dom parent */		
init : function(parentEl) {
	 //create an check box that will be our only tool control. 
	$(parentEl).append("&lt;input type=\"checkbox\" id=\"mouse-coords-tool-button\">get click board coords&lt;/input>");
	//add a mouse click listener in the paper
	$("#trivia-paper").click(gt.tools.mouseCoords._mouseCoordsMouseHandler);
},


/** this function indicates if this tool shoud be showed according to a game's data. 
 * This method will be called at least one, so this way the tool can define custom 
 * game's configuration for indicating if tool should be enabled, or passing other data. */
isEnabled : function(data) {
	return data.mouseCoordsToolEnabled;
},
/** internal mouse click handler */
_mouseCoordsMouseHandler : function(e) {
	//if the checkbox is checked, then show click's  coordinates
	if($("#mouse-coords-tool-button:checked").size()>0) {
		var pos = gt.getPositionFromEvent(e), 
			posPercent = gt.getPointPercent(pos);
		var s = "Click position in the board:\n"+
			"absolute: "+pos[0]+","+pos[1]+"\n"+
			"percentual: "+posPercent[0]+"%,"+posPercent[1]+"%";
		alert(s);
	}		
}	
		
};
  </programlisting>
  
  
  <para>
  Generatrivia is made using html, javascript, css and these main javascript libraries: 
  1) jquery.com for general javascript toolkit, 
  2) jqueryui.com for general gui, 
  3) raphaeljs.com for drawing and graphics.
  
  </para>
  
  <para>So when developing your own tools, you can use any of these toolkits for accomplish your purposes. </para>
  
  <note><para>Generatrivia framework api will be detailed in the following section. </para></note>
  </section>
  
  
  
  
  <section><title>Generatrivia framework api</title>
  
  <para>When writing your own generatrivia tools, it is useful to be familiarized with the 
  api of the framework.  </para>
  
  
<section><title>gt.initGame()</title>
<para>The main method for creating a game. It must be called from the html document
for starting the game. If you are writing your own html, 
make sure all necesary game scripts and css are loaded before starting the game, using jquery ready() function like this: </para>
<programlisting>
&lt;script>
$(document).ready(function(){
	gt.initGame();
});
&lt;/script>
</programlisting>

<para>gt.initGame() can be called with a configuration object parameter. This object can 
override game definition configuration in data.js. In fact an entire game definition 
object can be passed as parameter. It also accepts the property "gameParentElement" that can 
contains a reference to an html element that will contains the game inside.</para>
</section>
  </section>
  
  
  <section><title>Interesting usage scenarios</title>
  
  <section><title>Teaching</title>
  <para>Trivia game can be used by (high)school teachers for knowledge review, 
  for example the class before an exam. For example, a philosofy teacher, can perform a trivia with questions of different studied topics like epistemology, logic, ethics. Optionally the teacher want's 
its trivia to contain a nice famous painting as board background. Generatrivia 
is an excelent tool for this because the teacher only has to focus on its 
questions and answers and generatrivia will do the game work. It is up to the teacher
to spend time decorating the board with its own image. Also the rules of the game are defined in the classroom.
  </para>
  </section>

	<section><title>Defining and making your own board games</title>
  <para>... </para>
  </section>
  

  </section>
</article>
